<?xml version="1.0"?>
<teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>
BNC-Baby: a sampling of the British National Corpus
</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>
Selection, design, distribution</resp>
<name>Research Technologies Service, Oxford University</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt>
<resp>
Creation of original BNC
</resp>
<name>
BNC Consortium (OUP, Longman, UCREL, OUCS, Chambers)
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<editionStmt n="2.0">
<edition>Second Edition</edition>
</editionStmt>
<extent>Approximately four million words
</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<distributor>
Oxford University Computing Services
</distributor>
<address>
<addrLine>13 Banbury Road, Oxford OX2 6NN U.K.</addrLine>
<addrLine>Telephone:     +44 1865 273221</addrLine>
<addrLine>Facsimile:     +44 1865 273275</addrLine>
<addrLine>Internet mail: natcorp@oucs.ox.ac.uk</addrLine>
</address>
<idno type="BNC">BNC-B</idno>
 <availability>
        <para>This version of the British National Corpus is licenced for distribution by Oxford
University Computing Services. Each copy of the corpus must include a copy of
this corpus header and of the standard licence agreement. Any redistribution or
republishing of the corpus texts (the "BNC Processed Material") is strictly
forbidden.</para>
        <para>For information, the conditions of the Standard License Agreement are as
follows.</para>
        <para>(a) The BNC Consortium grants according to the terms and conditions
set out herein and in consideration of the payments specified herein
a non-exclusive, non-transferable Licence to the Licensee to use the
BNC Processed Material for the purposes of linguistic research
and/or the development of language products.</para>
        <para>(b) Distribution of the BNC Processed Material is restricted to the
Licensee or in the event of the Licensee being an organisation, to
the Licensee's research group. This group is defined as consisting
only of those Licensee's employees whom the Licensee authorises to
perform the work using the BNC Processed Material for the purposes
described in paragraph (a).</para>
        <para>(c) Members of the said research group must not, except as herein
provided, copy, publish or otherwise give to any third party access
to the whole or any part of the BNC Processed Material. It is the
responsibility of the Licensee to ensure that the members of the
said research group understand and abide by this restriction, and to
supervise their activities with respect to the BNC Processed
Material. Neither the Licensee nor members of the Licensee's said
research group may assign, transfer, lease, sell, rent, charge or
otherwise encumber the BNC Processed Material.</para>
        <para>(d) The BNC Processed Material may be installed at the place or places
of work of the said research group. The place of work is defined as
the computing systems that the members of a research group normally
use to conduct their research activities. It can include both work
and home computers, and is not restricted to a particular machine or
building.</para>
        <para>(e) Copies of the BNC Processed Material may be made for backup
purposes, or for the purposes of making data available to members of
the research group but the Licensee shall ensure that the BNC
Consortium's copyright notice is reproduced on all copies or parts
thereof of the BNC Processed Material. Any such copies will be
deemed to be part of the BNC Processed Material.</para>
        <para>(f) There is no restriction on the use of the Licensee's Results
except that the Licensee may not publish in print or electronic form
or exploit commercially in any form whatsoever any extracts from the
BNC Processed Material other than as permitted under the provisions
of the relevant copyright laws. </para>
        <para>(g) The BNC Consortium does not grant to the Licensee any rights
whatsoever to reproduce the BNC Texts or use all or any part of the
BNC Texts in commercial products or services in any way other than
would be permitted under the fair dealings provision of copyright
law.</para>
      </availability>
      <date value="2008-03-15">15 March 2008</date>
    </publicationStmt>
    <sourceDesc>
      <para>
The British National Corpus has no single source document. For details of the
source or sources used in the creation of each electronic text, see the individual
text headers. The principles and practices underlying selection and design of the
corpus are documented in the BNC User Reference Guide, a copy of which should be
supplied with it.</para>
    </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
    <projectDesc>
      <para>The British National Corpus (BNC) Consortium was formed in 1990, and
started work in 1991 on the three-year task of producing a
hundred-million word corpus of modern British English for use in
commercial and academic research. The first edition was published in
1994.</para>
      <para>A second edition (the World Edition) was produced during between 1998
and 2000. It contains a thorough revision of the part of speech tagging,
several corrections to the headers, and some minor revision of the SGML
tagging used.</para>
      <para>This edition is derived from the BNC World Edition but has been
converted to use XML throughout, and also to include explicit
lemmatization. </para>
      <para>The BNC is the result of of a unique collaboration between three major
U.K. dictionary publishers, two universities, and the British Library.
The dictionary publishers are Chambers Harrap, Longman, and Oxford
University Press; the universities are The Unit for Computer Research
into the English Language (UCREL) at Lancaster University; and Oxford
University Services (OUCS). </para>
      <para>The development of the BNC was funded by the commercial partners in
the consortium with assistance from the the U.K. government's Department
of Trade and Industry (DTI) and Science and Engineering Research Council
(SERC) under the Joint Framework for Information Technology
(JFIT).</para>
      <para>The British National Corpus is <list><item>
A *large* corpus: its hundred million words are made up of
ninety million from written and ten million from spoken
sources.
</item><item>
A *sample* corpus: it is composed of text samples,
generally of no more than 40,000 words, rather than of
complete works.
</item><item>
A *synchronic* corpus: it includes imaginative
texts dating from the 1960s to 1994; informative texts
dating from 1975 to 1994; and spoken texts gathered
primarily between 1990 and 1994.
</item><item>
A *general* corpus: it is not specifically
restricted to any particular subject field, register or
genre. It includes language from all age and social groups
and a broad spread of U.K. regions.
</item><item>
A *monolingual* British English Corpus: text
samples are substantially the product of British English
speakers. A small proportion of the words in the corpus are
in a foreign language or non-British English.
</item><item>
A *TEI-conformant* Corpus: texts in the corpus are
uniformly marked up according to the recommendations of the
Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), an international consortium
concerned with the mark-up of texts for use in academic
research. Originally expressed using Standardized General
Markup Language (SGML; IS 8879:1986), the corpus is now
encoded using XML.
</item></list></para>
      <para>Lexicography: The corpus provides a body of new data on word
meaning, grammar and usage. It yields empirical data on word
frequencies, word classes and spelling preferences, among other
things. It also reveals hitherto undocumented evidence about the
spoken language, with consequences that go far beyond the
immediate impact on dictionary-writing.</para>
      <para>Linguistic research: The corpus provides a standard basis for
investigating phenomena and testing competing linguistic
theories.</para>
      <para>Language technology: Statistical techniques, requiring very
large samples of text, are increasingly used in machine
translation, speech recognition, speech synthesizers, spelling
and grammar checkers for word-processing and desk-top
publishing, hand-held electronic books and other developments in
information technology.</para>
      <para>Teaching: The corpus provides a rich source of examples of
current usage for English Language Teaching, allowing more
frequent patterns of use to be distinguished from less frequent.
In addition, the corpus provides a valuable didactic resource
for use in many areas of higher education.</para>
      <para>As a model: Future TEI-conformant corpora, in English and
other languages, may base their designs on the experience gained
in the production of the BNC.</para>
    </projectDesc>
    <samplingDecl>
      <para>Definitive information on the sampling policies
applied during  construction of the BNC is provided in the associated
reference documentation. Different kinds of material were selected in
different ways. Half the spoken material was chosen by a demographic
sampling procedure, and the other half by sampling from
predetermined contexts. Written material was selected
randomly within the constraints of predetermined design criteria. The
object was to maximize variation within each sampling
frame.</para>
    </samplingDecl>
    <editorialDecl>
      <para>Material included in the BNC was produced by
several different agencies and went through several pre- and
post processing stages. An attempt has been made at consistency with
respect to such matters as: treatment of perceived errors in the
original (these are either silently corrected, or corrected with the
&lt;corr&gt; element); treatment of end-of-line hyphenation (for the
most part, end-of-line hyphenation has been removed); treatment of
punctuation marks (all single or double quotation marks have been
represented as &lt;c&gt; elements containing the appropriate Unicode
character); segmentation into &lt;s&gt; ("sentence"), &lt;mw&gt;
("multiword"), &lt;w&gt;("word"), and
&lt;c&gt; ("punctuation string") elements  has been carried uniformly
out across the whole corpus.</para>
      <para>Material was originally prepared variously by copy-typing,
scanning followed by OCR, and conversion from machine-readable
sources. All material was processed to a common SGML format, and all
subsequent processing, including addition of linguistic annotation,
conversion to XML, and most error correction, was done using a wide
range of software tools.</para>
    </editorialDecl>
    <refsDecl>
      <para>Canonical references to the BNC should be
constructed by taking the value of the n
attribute of the &lt;bncDoc&gt; element containing the target text, and
concatenating a dot separator, followed by the value of the n attribute of the
target &lt;s&gt; element containing the material to be referenced.</para>
      <para>Segments are numbered sequentially within each text or stext,
starting at 1. There may be gaps in the numeric sequence, as a
consequence of post-segmentation corrections.</para>
    </refsDecl>
    <classDecl>
      <taxonomy xml:id="DLee">
        <desc>David Lee's register and domain classification</desc>
        <bibl>
          <title>Register classification</title>
          <author>David Lee</author>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>http://members.xoom.com/davidlee00/genre_register.zip</pubPlace>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="COPAC">
        <desc>Bibliographic keywords from COPAC</desc>
        <bibl>
          <title>[Keyword classifications]</title>
          <imprint>
            <pubPlace>http://copac.ac.uk</pubPlace>
          </imprint>
        </bibl>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="textMode">
        <desc>Text mode</desc>
        <category xml:id="acad">
          <catDesc>Academic prose</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="demog">
          <catDesc>Unscripted conversation</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="fict">
          <catDesc>Imaginative prose</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="news">
          <catDesc>Newspapers and periodicals</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="derivedTextType">
        <desc>Text class</desc>
        <category xml:id="ACPROSE">
          <catDesc>Academic prose</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="FICTION">
          <catDesc>Fiction and verse</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="NONAC">
          <catDesc>Non-academic prose and biography</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="NEWS">
          <catDesc>Newspapers</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="OTHERPUB">
          <catDesc>Other published written material</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="UNPUB">
          <catDesc>Unpublished written material</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="CONVRSN">
          <catDesc>Spoken conversation</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="OTHERSP">
          <catDesc>Other spoken material</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>-->
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="allava">
        <desc>Availability</desc>
        <category xml:id="ALLAVA0">
          <catDesc>Ownership unclaimed</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="ALLAVA2">
          <catDesc>Worldwide rights cleared</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="ALLTYP">
        <desc>Text type</desc>
        <category xml:id="ALLTYP1">
          <catDesc>Spoken demographic</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="ALLTYP2">
          <catDesc>Spoken context-governed</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="ALLTYP3">
          <catDesc>Written books and periodicals</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="ALLTYP4">
          <catDesc>Written-to-be-spoken</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="ALLTYP5">
          <catDesc>Written miscellaneous</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="SCGDOM">
        <desc>Spoken context</desc>
        <category xml:id="SCGDOM1">
          <catDesc>Educational/Informative</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="SCGDOM2">
          <catDesc>Business</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="SCGDOM3">
          <catDesc>Public/Institutional</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="SCGDOM4">
          <catDesc>Leisure</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
    -->  <taxonomy xml:id="sdeage">
        <desc>Age-group</desc>
        <category xml:id="sdeage1">
          <catDesc>Respondent Age 0-14</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdeage2">
          <catDesc>Respondent Age 15-24</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdeage3">
          <catDesc>Respondent Age 25-34</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdeage4">
          <catDesc>Respondent Age 35-44</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdeage5">
          <catDesc>Respondent Age 45-59</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdeage6">
          <catDesc>Respondent Age 60+</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="sdecla">
        <desc>Social class</desc>
        <category xml:id="sdecla0">
          <catDesc>Unknown class</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdecla1">
          <catDesc>AB respondent</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdecla2">
          <catDesc>C1 respondent</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdecla3">
          <catDesc>C2 respondent</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdecla4">
          <catDesc>DE respondent</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="sdesex">
        <desc>Sex</desc>
        <category xml:id="sdesex0">
          <catDesc>Respondent sex unknown</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdesex1">
          <catDesc>Male respondent</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sdesex2">
          <catDesc>Female respondent</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="spolog">
        <desc>Interaction type</desc>
        <category xml:id="spolog1">
          <catDesc>Monologue</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="spolog2">
          <catDesc>Dialogue</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
 -->     <taxonomy xml:id="sporeg">
        <desc>Region</desc>
        <category xml:id="sporeg0">
          <catDesc>Unknown</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sporeg1">
          <catDesc>South </catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sporeg2">
          <catDesc>Midlands</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="sporeg3">
          <catDesc>North</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="WRIAUD">
        <desc>Audience age</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRIAUD1">
          <catDesc>Child audience</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAUD2">
          <catDesc>Teenager audience</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAUD3">
          <catDesc>Adult audience</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAUD4">
          <catDesc>Any audience</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="WRITAS">
        <desc>Audience sex</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRITAS1">
          <catDesc>Male audience</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRITAS2">
          <catDesc>Female audience</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRITAS3">
          <catDesc>Mixed audience</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRITAS0">
          <catDesc>Unknown audience</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="WRIAAG">
        <desc>Author age-group</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG0">
          <catDesc>Author age unknown</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG1">
          <catDesc>Author age 0-14</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG2">
          <catDesc>Author age 15-24</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG3">
          <catDesc>Author age 25-34</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG4">
          <catDesc>Author age 35-44</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG5">
          <catDesc>Author age 45-59</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAAG6">
          <catDesc>Author age 60+</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="WRIAD">
        <desc>Domicile</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRIAD1">
          <catDesc>Author domicile UK and Ireland</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAD2">
          <catDesc>Author domicile Commonwealth</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAD3">
          <catDesc>Author domicile Continental Europe</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAD4">
          <catDesc>Author domicile USA</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAD5">
          <catDesc>Author domicile Elsewhere</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIAD0">
          <catDesc>Author domicile Unknown</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
    -->  <taxonomy xml:id="wriase">
        <desc>Sex of author</desc>
        <category xml:id="wriase0">
          <catDesc>Author sex Unknown</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wriase1">
          <catDesc>Author sex Male</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wriase2">
          <catDesc>Author sex Female</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wriase3">
          <catDesc>Author sex Mixed</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="WRIATY">
        <desc>Author type</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRIATY1">
          <catDesc>Corporate author</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIATY2">
          <catDesc>Multiple author</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIATY3">
          <catDesc>Sole author</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIATY0">
          <catDesc>Unknown author</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
    -->  <taxonomy xml:id="wrista">
        <desc>Estimated circulation size</desc>
        <category xml:id="wrista0">
          <catDesc>Unknown circulation</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wrista1">
          <catDesc>Low circulation</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wrista2">
          <catDesc>Medium circulation</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wrista3">
          <catDesc>High circulation</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="WRILEV">
        <desc>Written Difficulty</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRILEV1">
          <catDesc>Low difficulty</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRILEV2">
          <catDesc>Medium difficulty</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRILEV3">
          <catDesc>High difficulty</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
    -->  <taxonomy xml:id="wridom">
        <desc>Written Domain</desc>
        <category xml:id="wridom1">
          <catDesc>Imaginative</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom2">
          <catDesc>Informative: natural &amp; pure science</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom3">
          <catDesc>Informative: applied science</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom4">
          <catDesc>Informative: social science</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom5">
          <catDesc>Informative: world affairs</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom6">
          <catDesc>Informative: commerce &amp; finance</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom7">
          <catDesc>Informative: arts</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom8">
          <catDesc>Informative: belief &amp; thought</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="wridom9">
          <catDesc>Informative: leisure</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="WRIMED">
        <desc>Written Medium</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRIMED1">
          <catDesc>Book</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIMED2">
          <catDesc>Periodical</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIMED3">
          <catDesc>Miscellaneous published</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIMED4">
          <catDesc>Miscellaneous unpublished</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIMED5">
          <catDesc>To-be-spoken</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
    -->  <taxonomy xml:id="alltim">
        <desc>Publication date</desc>
        <category xml:id="alltim1">
          <catDesc>1960-1974</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="alltim2">
          <catDesc>1975-1984</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="alltim3">
          <catDesc>1985-1993</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="alltim0">
          <catDesc>Unknown</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
<!--      <taxonomy xml:id="WRIPP">
        <desc>Publication place</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP0">
          <catDesc>Unknown publication place</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP1">
          <catDesc>UK (unspecific) publication</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP2">
          <catDesc>Ireland publication</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP6">
          <catDesc>United States publication</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP3">
          <catDesc>UK: North (north of Mersey-Humber line) publication</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP4">
          <catDesc>UK: Midlands (north of Bristol Channel-Wash line) publication</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRIPP5">
          <catDesc>UK: South (south of Bristol Channel-Wash line) publication</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>
      <taxonomy xml:id="WRISAM">
        <desc>Sampling type</desc>
        <category xml:id="WRISAM0">
          <catDesc>Unknown sampling</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRISAM1">
          <catDesc>Whole text</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRISAM2">
          <catDesc>Beginning sample</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRISAM3">
          <catDesc>Middle sample</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRISAM4">
          <catDesc>End sample</catDesc>
        </category>
        <category xml:id="WRISAM5">
          <catDesc>Composite sample</catDesc>
        </category>
      </taxonomy>-->


    </classDecl>
    <xairaSpecification>
      <xairaList type="elementSpec">
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="*">
          <desc>global attributes</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="id" ns="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace">
              <desc>a name or number used to label any element</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="activity">
          <desc>(activity) contains a brief informal description of what a participant in a
language interaction is doing other than speaking, if anything.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="spont">
              <desc>level of spontaneity</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="address">
          <desc>contains a postal or other address, for example of a
publisher, an organization, or an individual.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="age">
          <desc>specifies the age in years of a recorded participant at the time of the
  recording in which they participate. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="align">
          <desc>marks an temporal alignment point within transcribed speech</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="with">
              <desc>supplies an arbitrary identifier; all
      elements specifying the same value for this attribute are
      understood to be aligned with each other in time.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="attDef">
          <desc>(attribute definition) provides the definition for a single attribute.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>(namespace) specifies the namespace to which this attribute belongs</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="attList">
          <desc>contains documentation for all the attributes associated with this
element, as a series of attDef elements.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="attributePolicy">
          <desc>specifies the indexing policy to be used for one or more
attributes. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>identifies the attribute to which the
indexing policy applies</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>specifies the required indexing policy
</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="none">
                  <desc>no part of the attribute will be indexed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="jointo">
                  <desc>the attribute supplies an identifier
which can be linked to from elsewhere</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="joinfrom">
                  <desc>the value of the attribute is used as
an  identifier on some other element</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="taxonomy">
                  <desc>the value of the attribute is used to
supply a key for some predefined codebook or taxonomy of possible
values</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="author">
          <desc>in a bibliographic reference, contains the name of the author(s),
personal or corporate,
of a work; the primary statement of responsibility for any
bibliographic item. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="domicile">
              <desc>main country of residence where known</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>internal identifier</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="born">
              <desc>year of birth where known</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="availability">
          <desc>supplies information about the availability of a text, for
  example any restrictions on its use or distribution, its copyright
  status, etc.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="bibliography" ns="http://xaira.org/ns/1.0/bibliography">
	  <desc>contains bibliographic description of a source text in
	  the corpus, extracted from the text itself</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="bibl">
          <desc>(bibliographic citation) contains a loosely-structured bibliographic citation of which
the sub-components may or may not be explicitly tagged. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="bnc">
          <desc>(TEI corpus) contains the whole of a TEI encoded corpus, comprising a
single corpus header and one or more TEI elements, each containing
a single text header and a text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="bncDoc">
          <desc>contains a distinct document within the corpus, either spoken
 or written.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="c">
          <desc>(character) contains a significant punctuation mark as identified by the CLAWS tagger. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="c5">
              <desc>the CLAWS 5 code associated with this punctuation
   mark. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="PUN">
                  <desc>any separating punctuation mark</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PUL">
                  <desc>opening round or square parenthesis</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PUR">
                  <desc>closing round or square parenthesis</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PUQ">
                  <desc>any quotation mark</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="catDesc">
          <desc>(category description) provides a description for one category within the text taxonomies
provided in the corpus header.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="catRef">
          <desc>(category reference) provides a list of codes identifying the categories to which
this text has been assigned, each code referencing a category element
declared in the corpus header.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="targets">
              <desc>identifies the categories concerned
   </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="category">
          <desc>(category) defines a single category within a taxonomy of texts.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="change">
          <desc>summarizes a particular change or correction made
to a particular version of an electronic text which is
shared between several researchers.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="date">
              <desc>supplies the date of the change in standard form,  i.e. yyyy-mm-dd.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="who">
              <desc>indicates the person, or group of
	people, to whom the element content is ascribed.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="classCode">
          <desc>(classCode) contains the classification code used for this text in some
standard classification system.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="scheme">
              <desc>identifies the classification system or taxonomy in use.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="classDecl">
          <desc>(classification declarations) contains one or more taxonomies defining any classificatory
codes used elsewhere in the text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="collate">
          <desc>supplies any additional ICU-conformant collating rules to be used when sorting
words in the corpus. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="corr">
          <desc>(correction) contains the correct form of a passage apparently erroneous in the copy text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="sic">
              <desc>contains verbatim text which has been corrected, or an empty string if
the correction consists of an addition. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="resp">
              <desc>a code identifying the agency responsible for making the
correction.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="creation">
          <desc>contains information about the creation of a text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="date">
              <desc>supplies the year of original composition, if known; or 000-00-00 if
the date is unknown. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="date">
          <desc>contains a date in any format.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="value">
              <desc>supplies a standardized representation of the date</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="defaultVal">
          <desc>specifies the default declared value for an attribute.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="desc">
          <desc>(description) contains a brief description of the purpose and application for
an element, attribute, or attribute value.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="dialect">
          <desc>contains an informal description of the regional variety of
English used by a participant in a spoken text. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="distributor">
          <desc>supplies the name of a person or other agency responsible for the
distribution of a text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="div">
          <desc>(text division) contains a subdivision of the front, body, or back of a
text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>for a spoken text, identities the tape corresponding to this
division. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="decls">
              <desc>for a spoken text, identities the declarations (for setting,
recording etc.) in the header which apply to this
division. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="level">
              <desc>specifies the hierarchic level of this division as a number
between  1 (outermost or largest division) and 4
(innermost or smallest). </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>identifies the type or function of the division (for a written text).</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="edition">
          <desc>(Edition) describes the particularities of one edition of a text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>supplies an identifying number for the edition</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="editionStmt">
          <desc>(edition statement) groups information relating to one edition of a text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="editor">
          <desc>(editor) secondary statement of responsibility for a
bibliographic item, for example the name of an individual, institution
or organization, (or of several such) acting as editor, compiler,
translator, etc. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>supplies a number for the editor where multiple editors are
specified for a single text</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="editorialDecl">
          <desc>(editorial practice declaration) provides details of editorial principles and practices applied
during the encoding of a text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="elementPolicy">
          <desc>specifies the xaira indexing policy to be used for one or more
elements. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>identifies the element to which the
indexing policy applies.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>specifies the required indexing policy.
</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="none">
                  <desc>no part of the element or its
content will be indexed.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="children">
                  <desc>no part of the element will be
indexed, but any child elements will be.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="content">
                  <desc>only the text and child content of the element will be
indexed.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="markup">
                  <desc>only the start and end tags for the
element and any child elements not otherwise specified will be
indexed.</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="encodingDesc">
          <desc>(Encoding description) documents the relationship between an electronic text and the
source or sources from which it was derived.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="event">
          <desc>(Event) any phenomenon or occurrence, not necessarily vocalized or
communicative, for example incidental noises or other events affecting
communication.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="desc">
              <desc>provides a brief description of the event</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="dur">
              <desc>(duration) indicates the duration of the element in minutes. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="extent">
          <desc>specifies the approximate size of the text, in orthographic
words, w elements, and s elements </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="fileDesc">
          <desc>(File Description) contains a full bibliographic description of an electronic
file.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="gap">
          <desc>(omitted material) indicates a point where material has been omitted from the
transcription. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="desc">
              <desc>briefly describes the material which has been omitted. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="reason">
              <desc>gives further details of the reason for omission.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="resp">
              <desc>indicates the agency responsible for the
	intervention or interpretation, for example an editor or transcriber.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="gi">
          <desc>(generic identifier) contains the name (generic identifier) of an element.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="head">
          <desc>(heading) contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section,
or the heading of a list, glossary, manuscript description, etc.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc/>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="MAIN">
                  <desc>a major heading. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="SUB">
                  <desc>any sub-heading.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="BYLINE">
                  <desc>a sub-heading providing the name of a
journalist or other source of a newspaper report.</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="hi">
          <desc>(highlighted) marks a word or phrase as graphically distinct from the
surrounding text, for reasons concerning which no claim is
made. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="ident">
          <desc>contains an identifier or name for an object of some kind in a formal language</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="idno">
          <desc>(identifying number) supplies an identifying code for a text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>categorizes the code number used.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>categorizes the number, for example as an ISBN or other
         standard series.
   </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="imprint">
          <desc>groups information relating to the publication or distribution
  of a bibliographic item.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>internal identifier</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="item">
          <desc>contains one
component of a list.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="joinTo">
          <desc>supplies a list of element names carrying an attribute which has
been specified with the xaira "joinTo" indexing policy.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="keywords">
          <desc>(Keywords) contains a list of keywords or phrases identifying the topic or
nature of a text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="scheme">
              <desc>identifies the controlled vocabulary within which the set of
  keywords concerned is defined.
   </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="l">
          <desc>(verse line) contains a single, possibly incomplete, line of verse.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="label">
          <desc>contains the label associated with an item in a list; in
glossaries, marks the term being defined.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="labelGen">
          <desc>specifies the label to be generated for the parent reference. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="change">
              <desc>specifies when the new label is to be generated. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="onStart">
                  <desc>a new label is generated when a new
instance of the scope-defining element is found, and remains in force
until the next such element is found.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="within">
                  <desc>a new label is generated when a new
instance of the scope-defining element is found, and remains in force
until that instance ends.</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="langUsage">
          <desc>(language usage) describes the languages, sublanguages, registers, dialects etc.
represented within a text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="language">
          <desc>characterizes a single language or sublanguage used within a
  text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>Supplies a language code constructed as defined in RFC 3066 (or
      its successor) which is used to identify the language documented
      by this element, and which is referenced by the global xml:lang attribute.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="lg">
          <desc>(line group) contains a group of verse lines functioning as a formal unit,
e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph, etc.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="list">
          <desc>contains any sequence of items organized as a list.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="locale">
          <desc>(locale) contains a brief informal description of the nature of a
place for example a room, a restaurant, a park bench etc.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="mw">
          <desc>contains a multi-word unit as identified by CLAWS, that is, a
sequence of individual tokens which function as a single
unit and can be given a single part of speech code. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="c5">
              <desc>supplies the CLAWS 5 code associated with this word.</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="AJ0">
                  <desc>Adjective (general or positive) (e.g. good, old, beautiful)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJC">
                  <desc>Comparative adjective (e.g. better, older)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJS">
                  <desc>Superlative adjective (e.g. best, oldest)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AT0">
                  <desc>Article (e.g. the, a, an, no)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AV0">
                  <desc>General adverb: an adverb not subclassified as AVP or AVQ (see below) (e.g. often, well, longer (adv.), furthest.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVP">
                  <desc>Adverb particle (e.g. up, off, out)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVQ">
                  <desc>Wh-adverb (e.g. when, where, how, why, wherever) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJC">
                  <desc>Coordinating conjunction (e.g. and, or, but)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJS">
                  <desc>Subordinating conjunction (e.g. although, when)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJT">
                  <desc>The subordinating conjunction that</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CRD">
                  <desc>Cardinal number (e.g. one, 3, fifty-five, 3609)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DPS">
                  <desc>Possessive determiner-pronoun (e.g. your, their, his)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DT0">
                  <desc>General determiner-pronoun: i.e. a determiner-pronoun which is not a DTQ or an AT0. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DTQ">
                  <desc>Wh-determiner-pronoun (e.g. which, what, whose, whichever) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="EX0">
                  <desc>Existential there, i.e. there occurring in the there is ... or there are ... construction</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ITJ">
                  <desc>Interjection or other isolate (e.g. oh, yes, mhm, wow)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN0">
                  <desc>Common noun, neutral for number (e.g. aircraft, data, committee) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1">
                  <desc>Singular common noun (e.g. pencil, goose, time, revelation)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN2">
                  <desc>Plural common noun (e.g. pencils, geese, times, revelations)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NP0">
                  <desc>Proper noun (e.g. London, Michael, Mars, IBM) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ORD">
                  <desc>Ordinal numeral (e.g. first, sixth, 77th, last) .</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNI">
                  <desc>Indefinite pronoun (e.g. none, everything, one [as pronoun], nobody)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNP">
                  <desc>Personal pronoun (e.g. I, you, them, ours)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNQ">
                  <desc>Wh-pronoun (e.g. who, whoever, whom)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNX">
                  <desc>Reflexive pronoun (e.g. myself, yourself, itself, ourselves)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="POS">
                  <desc>The possessive or genitive marker 's or '</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRF">
                  <desc>The preposition of</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRP">
                  <desc>Preposition (except for of) (e.g. about, at, in, on, on behalf of, with)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="TO0">
                  <desc>Infinitive marker to</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="UNC">
                  <desc>Unclassified items which are not appropriately considered as items of the English lexicon.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBB">
                  <desc>The present tense forms of the verb BE, except for is, 's: i.e. am, are, 'm, 're and be [subjunctive or imperative]</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBD">
                  <desc>The past tense forms of the verb BE: was and were</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of the verb BE: being</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of the verb BE: be</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of the verb BE: been</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of the verb BE: is, 's</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDB">
                  <desc>The finite base form of the verb BE: do</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDD">
                  <desc>The past tense form of the verb DO: did</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of the verb DO: doing</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of the verb DO: do</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of the verb DO: done</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of the verb DO: does, 's</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHB">
                  <desc>The finite base form of the verb HAVE: have, 've</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHD">
                  <desc>The past tense form of the verb HAVE: had, 'd</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of the verb HAVE: having</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of the verb HAVE: have</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of the verb HAVE: had</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of the verb HAVE: has, 's</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VM0">
                  <desc>Modal auxiliary verb (e.g. will, would, can, could, 'll, 'd)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVB">
                  <desc>The finite base form of lexical verbs (e.g. forget, send, live, return) [Including the imperative and present subjunctive]</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVD">
                  <desc>The past tense form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgot, sent, lived, returned)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgetting, sending, living, returning)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of lexical verbs (e.g. forget, send, live, return)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgotten, sent, lived, returned)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgets, sends, lives, returns)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="XX0">
                  <desc>The negative particle not or n't </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ZZ0">
                  <desc>Alphabetical symbols (e.g. A, a, B, b, c, d)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-AV0">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe AV0 (adverb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-VVD">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe VVD (verb past tense)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-VVG">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe VVG (-ing verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-VVN">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe VVN (verb past participle)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AV0-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably AV0 (adverb), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVP-PRP">
                  <desc>Probably AVP (adverb particle), but maybe PRP (preposition)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVQ-CJS">
                  <desc>Probably AVQ (wh- adverb), but maybe CJS (subordinating conjunction)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJS-AVQ">
                  <desc>Probably CJS (subordinating conjunction), but maybe AVQ (wh- adverb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJS-PRP">
                  <desc>Probably CJS (subordinating conjunction), but maybe PRP (preposition)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJT-DT0">
                  <desc>Probably CJT ("that" as conjunction), but maybe DT0 (determiner)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CRD-PNI">
                  <desc>Probably CRD (number), but maybe PNI (indefinite pronoun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DT0-CJT">
                  <desc>Probably DT0 (determiner), but maybe CJT ("that" as conjunction)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-NP0">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe NP0 (proper noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-VVB">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe VVB (verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-VVG">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe VVG (-ing verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN2-VVZ">
                  <desc>Probably NN2 (plural noun), but maybe VVZ (-s verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NP0-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably NP0 (proper noun), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNI-CRD">
                  <desc>Probably PNI (indefinite pronoun), but maybe CRD (number)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRP-AVP">
                  <desc>Probably PRP (preposition), but maybe AVP (adverb particle)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRP-CJS">
                  <desc>Probably PRP (preposition), but maybe CJS (subordinating conjunction)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVB-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably VVB (verb), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVD-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably VVD (verb past tense), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVD-VVN">
                  <desc>Probably VVD (verb past tense), but maybe VVN (verb past participle)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVG-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably VVG (-ing verb), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVG-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably VVG (-ing verb), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVN-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably VVN (verb past participle), but maybe AJ0</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVN-VVD">
                  <desc>Probably VVN (verb past participle), but maybe VVD (verb past tense)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVZ-NN2">
                  <desc>Probably VVZ (-s verb), but maybe NN2 (plural noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="name">
          <desc>(name, proper noun) contains a proper noun or noun phrase.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="nameList">
          <desc>supplies a list of element names or attribute identifiers</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="namespace">
          <desc>supplies the formal name of the namespace to which the elements
documented by its children belong. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="name">
              <desc>the full formal name of the namespace concerned.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="note">
          <desc>contains a note or annotation.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="place">
              <desc/>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>internal identifier</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="occupation">
          <desc>contains an informal description of a person's trade,
profession or occupation.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="p">
          <desc>(paragraph) marks paragraphs in prose.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>indicates how the paragraph is displayed</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="para">
          <desc>contains descriptive text appearing within components of a TEI header</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="particDesc">
          <desc>(participation description) describes the identifiable speakers, voices, or other participants
in a linguistic interaction. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>internal identifier</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="pause">
          <desc>a pause either between or within utterances.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="dur">
              <desc>(duration) indicates the duration of the element in minutes. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="pb">
          <desc>(page break) marks the boundary between one page of a text and the next
in a standard reference system.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>gives the number of the page beginning here</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="persName">
          <desc>(personal name) contains a proper noun or proper-noun phrase referring to a
  person, possibly including any or all of the person's forenames,
  surnames, honorifics, added names, etc.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="persNote">
          <desc>contains any additional information supplied about a participant in a spoken text </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="person">
          <desc>provides information about an identifiable individual, for
example a participant in a language interaction, or a person referred
to in a historical source.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="placeName">
          <desc>(place name) contains an absolute or relative place name. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="pp">
          <desc>supplies page numbers for a bibliographic citation.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="profileDesc">
          <desc>(text-profile description) provides a detailed description of non-bibliographic aspects of a
text, specifically the languages and sublanguages used, the situation in
which it was produced, the participants and their setting.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="projectDesc">
          <desc>(project description) describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an electronic
file was encoded, together with any other relevant information
concerning the process by which it was assembled or collected.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="pubPlace">
          <desc>contains the name of the place where a bibliographic item was
published.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="publicationStmt">
          <desc>(publication statement) groups information concerning the publication or distribution
of an electronic or other text. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="publisher">
          <desc>provides the name of the organization responsible for
the publication or distribution of a bibliographic item.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="quote">
          <desc>(quotation) contains a phrase or passage attributed by the narrator or
author to some agency external to the text. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="recording">
          <desc>(recording event) details of an audio or video recording event
used as the source of a spoken text, either directly or from
a public broadcast. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="recordingStmt">
          <desc>(recording statement) describes a set of recordings used in transcription of a
spoken text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="refsDecl">
          <desc>(references declaration) provides documentation for the reference system applicable to
the corpus. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="relation">
          <desc>(relationship) describes any kind of relationship or linkage amongst a specified
group of participants.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="active">
              <desc>identifies the active participants in a non-mutual
relationship, or all the participants in a mutual one.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="mutual">
              <desc>supplies a list of participants amongst all of whom the relationship holds equally.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="name">
              <desc>supplies a name for the kind of  relationship of which
	this is an instance.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="passive">
              <desc>identifies the passive participants in a non-mutual
relationship.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="resp">
          <desc>contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's
  intellectual responsibility.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="respStmt">
          <desc>(statement of responsibility) supplies a statement of responsibility for someone responsible
  for the intellectual content of a text, edition, recording, or
  series, where the specialized elements for authors, editors, etc. do
  not suffice or do not apply.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="revisionDesc">
          <desc>(revision description) summarizes the revision history for a file.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="s">
          <desc>(s-unit) contains a sentence-like division of a text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="n">
              <desc>sequence number </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="samplingDecl">
          <desc>(sampling declaration) contains a prose description of the rationale and methods used
in sampling texts in the creation of a corpus or collection.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="setting">
          <desc>(setting) describes one particular setting in which a language
  interaction takes place.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="settingDesc">
          <desc>(setting description) describes the setting or settings within which a language
interaction takes place, either as a prose description or as a
series of setting elements.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="shift">
          <desc>(Shift) marks the point at which some paralinguistic feature of a series of
utterances by any one speaker changes.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="new">
              <desc>specifies the new state of the paralinguistic feature specified.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="sourceDesc">
          <desc>supplies a description of the source text(s) from
which an electronic text was derived or generated.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="sp">
          <desc>(speech) An individual speech in a performance text, or a passage
	  presented as such in a prose or verse text.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="who">
              <desc>indicates the person, or group of
	people, to whom the element content is ascribed.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="speaker">
          <desc>A specialized form of heading or label, giving the name of
one or more speakers in a dramatic text or fragment.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="stage">
          <desc>(stage direction) contains any kind of stage direction within a dramatic text or
fragment.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="rend">
              <desc>a code briefly characterising the way the element content was originally
presented. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="bo">
                  <desc>bold weight font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="bx">
                  <desc>boxed</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="hi">
                  <desc>superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ib">
                  <desc>italic and bold</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ih">
                  <desc>italic superscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="il">
                  <desc>italic subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="it">
                  <desc>italic font</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="iu">
                  <desc>italic and underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lo">
                  <desc>subscript</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="qc">
                  <desc>centre-aligned</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ro">
                  <desc>roman within italic</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="st">
                  <desc>strike-out</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ub">
                  <desc>bold underlined </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ul">
                  <desc>underlined</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="xx">
                  <desc>crossed-out</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="stext">
          <desc>contains a single spoken text, i.e. a transcription or
collection of transcriptions from a single source. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>specifies the type of spoken  text. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="CONVRSN">
                  <desc>demographically sampled conversation</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="OTHERSP">
                  <desc>any other spoken text</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="tagUsage">
          <desc>(tagUsage) supplies information about the usage of a specific element
within a text. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="gi">
              <desc>the name (generic identifier)
of the element indicated by the tag.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="occurs">
              <desc>specifies the number of occurrences of this element within the text.
 </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="tagsDecl">
          <desc>(tagging declaration) provides information about the XML elements actually used within
a BNC text</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="taxonomy">
          <desc>(taxonomy) defines a typology used to classify texts either implicitly, by
means of a bibliographic citation, or explicitly by a structured
taxonomy.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="teiHeader">
          <desc>(TEI Header) supplies the descriptive and declarative information making
	up an electronic title page prefixed to every TEI-conformant
	text.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="term">
          <desc>contains a word or phrase used to describe the topic or nature of a text. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="wtext">
          <desc>contains a single written text. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>specifies the type of written text.</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="ACPROSE">
                  <desc>Academic prose</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="FICTION">
                  <desc>Fiction and verse</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NEWS">
                  <desc>Newspapers</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NONAC">
                  <desc>Non-academic prose and biography</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="OTHERPUB">
                  <desc>Other published materials</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="UNPUB">
                  <desc>Unpublished materials</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="textClass">
          <desc>(text classification) groups information which describes the nature or topic of a text
in terms of a standard classification scheme, thesaurus, etc.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="title">
          <desc>contains the full title of a work of any kind.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="level">
              <desc>indicates the bibliographic level of this title</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="titleStmt">
          <desc>(title statement) groups information about the title of a work and those
responsible for its intellectual content.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="tokenize">
          <desc>supplies any additional ICU-conformant rules to be used
when tokenization is performed by xaira rather than by explicit XML markup. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="trunc">
          <desc>contains one or more truncated words in transcribed speech.</desc>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="u">
          <desc>(utterance) a stretch of speech usually preceded and followed by
silence or by a change of speaker.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="who">
              <desc>indicates the person, or group of
	people, to whom the element content is ascribed.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="unclear">
          <desc>contains a word, phrase, or passage which cannot be transcribed
with certainty because it is illegible or inaudible in the source.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="dur">
              <desc>(duration) indicates the duration of the element in minutes. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="valItem">
          <desc>(value definition) contains a single value and gloss  pair for an attribute.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="valList">
          <desc>(value list) contains one or more valItem elements defining possible
  values for an attribute.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="copyOf">
              <desc>supplies the identifier of a previously-defined value list to be
used at this point</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>specifies the extensibility of the list of attribute values
      specified.
      </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="closed">
                  <desc>(only the values specified are permitted.) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="semi">
                  <desc>(all the values specified should be supported, but
	  other values are legal and software should have appropriate
	  fallback processing for them.
	  ) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="open">
                  <desc>(the values specified are sample values only.) </desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="valSource">
          <desc>specifies where the indexer is to find a value. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>indicates the kind of value to be found. </desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="element">
                  <desc>element content. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="attribute">
                  <desc>attribute content. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="pseudo">
                  <desc>content returned by one of the pseudo-
functions count(), sysid(), or lineno() </desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="caseFold">
              <desc>indicates whether the value required should be casefolded or
not. </desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="vocal">
          <desc>(Vocalized semi-lexical) any vocalized but not necessarily lexical phenomenon, for example
voiced pauses, non-lexical backchannels, etc.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="desc">
              <desc>provides a brief description of the vocal event</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="dur">
              <desc>(duration) indicates the duration of the element in minutes. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="who">
              <desc>indicates the person, or group of
	people, to whom the element content is ascribed.</desc>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="w">
          <desc>(word) represents a grammatical (not necessarily orthographic) word.</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="pos">
              <desc>supplies a simplified  part-of-speech code.</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="ADJ">
                  <desc>adjective</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ADV">
                  <desc>adverb</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ART">
                  <desc>article</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CONJ">
                  <desc>conjunction</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="INTERJ">
                  <desc>interjection</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PREP">
                  <desc>preposition</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRON">
                  <desc>pronoun</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="STOP">
                  <desc>punctuation</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="SUBST">
                  <desc>substantive</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="UNC">
                  <desc>unclassified or non-lexical word</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VERB">
                  <desc>verb</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="hw">
              <desc>specifies the headword under which this lexical unit is
      conventionally grouped, where known.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="c5">
              <desc>supplies the CLAWS 5 code associated with this word.</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="AJ0">
                  <desc>Adjective (general or positive) (e.g. good, old, beautiful)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJC">
                  <desc>Comparative adjective (e.g. better, older)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJS">
                  <desc>Superlative adjective (e.g. best, oldest)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AT0">
                  <desc>Article (e.g. the, a, an, no)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AV0">
                  <desc>General adverb: an adverb not subclassified as AVP or AVQ (see below) (e.g. often, well, longer (adv.), furthest.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVP">
                  <desc>Adverb particle (e.g. up, off, out)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVQ">
                  <desc>Wh-adverb (e.g. when, where, how, why, wherever) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJC">
                  <desc>Coordinating conjunction (e.g. and, or, but)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJS">
                  <desc>Subordinating conjunction (e.g. although, when)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJT">
                  <desc>The subordinating conjunction that</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CRD">
                  <desc>Cardinal number (e.g. one, 3, fifty-five, 3609)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DPS">
                  <desc>Possessive determiner-pronoun (e.g. your, their, his)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DT0">
                  <desc>General determiner-pronoun: i.e. a determiner-pronoun which is not a DTQ or an AT0. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DTQ">
                  <desc>Wh-determiner-pronoun (e.g. which, what, whose, whichever) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="EX0">
                  <desc>Existential there, i.e. there occurring in the there is ... or there are ... construction</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ITJ">
                  <desc>Interjection or other isolate (e.g. oh, yes, mhm, wow)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN0">
                  <desc>Common noun, neutral for number (e.g. aircraft, data, committee) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1">
                  <desc>Singular common noun (e.g. pencil, goose, time, revelation)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN2">
                  <desc>Plural common noun (e.g. pencils, geese, times, revelations)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NP0">
                  <desc>Proper noun (e.g. London, Michael, Mars, IBM) </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ORD">
                  <desc>Ordinal numeral (e.g. first, sixth, 77th, last) .</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNI">
                  <desc>Indefinite pronoun (e.g. none, everything, one [as pronoun], nobody)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNP">
                  <desc>Personal pronoun (e.g. I, you, them, ours)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNQ">
                  <desc>Wh-pronoun (e.g. who, whoever, whom)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNX">
                  <desc>Reflexive pronoun (e.g. myself, yourself, itself, ourselves)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="POS">
                  <desc>The possessive or genitive marker 's or '</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRF">
                  <desc>The preposition of</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRP">
                  <desc>Preposition (except for of) (e.g. about, at, in, on, on behalf of, with)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="TO0">
                  <desc>Infinitive marker to</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="UNC">
                  <desc>Unclassified items which are not appropriately considered as items of the English lexicon.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBB">
                  <desc>The present tense forms of the verb BE, except for is, 's: i.e. am, are, 'm, 're and be [subjunctive or imperative]</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBD">
                  <desc>The past tense forms of the verb BE: was and were</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of the verb BE: being</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of the verb BE: be</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of the verb BE: been</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VBZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of the verb BE: is, 's</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDB">
                  <desc>The finite base form of the verb BE: do</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDD">
                  <desc>The past tense form of the verb DO: did</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of the verb DO: doing</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of the verb DO: do</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of the verb DO: done</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VDZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of the verb DO: does, 's</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHB">
                  <desc>The finite base form of the verb HAVE: have, 've</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHD">
                  <desc>The past tense form of the verb HAVE: had, 'd</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of the verb HAVE: having</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of the verb HAVE: have</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of the verb HAVE: had</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VHZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of the verb HAVE: has, 's</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VM0">
                  <desc>Modal auxiliary verb (e.g. will, would, can, could, 'll, 'd)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVB">
                  <desc>The finite base form of lexical verbs (e.g. forget, send, live, return) [Including the imperative and present subjunctive]</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVD">
                  <desc>The past tense form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgot, sent, lived, returned)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVG">
                  <desc>The -ing form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgetting, sending, living, returning)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVI">
                  <desc>The infinitive form of lexical verbs (e.g. forget, send, live, return)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVN">
                  <desc>The past participle form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgotten, sent, lived, returned)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVZ">
                  <desc>The -s form of lexical verbs (e.g. forgets, sends, lives, returns)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="XX0">
                  <desc>The negative particle not or n't </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="ZZ0">
                  <desc>Alphabetical symbols (e.g. A, a, B, b, c, d)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-AV0">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe AV0 (adverb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-VVD">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe VVD (verb past tense)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-VVG">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe VVG (-ing verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AJ0-VVN">
                  <desc>Probably AJ0 (adjective), but maybe VVN (verb past participle)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AV0-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably AV0 (adverb), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVP-PRP">
                  <desc>Probably AVP (adverb particle), but maybe PRP (preposition)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="AVQ-CJS">
                  <desc>Probably AVQ (wh- adverb), but maybe CJS (subordinating conjunction)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJS-AVQ">
                  <desc>Probably CJS (subordinating conjunction), but maybe AVQ (wh- adverb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJS-PRP">
                  <desc>Probably CJS (subordinating conjunction), but maybe PRP (preposition)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CJT-DT0">
                  <desc>Probably CJT ("that" as conjunction), but maybe DT0 (determiner)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="CRD-PNI">
                  <desc>Probably CRD (number), but maybe PNI (indefinite pronoun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="DT0-CJT">
                  <desc>Probably DT0 (determiner), but maybe CJT ("that" as conjunction)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-NP0">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe NP0 (proper noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-VVB">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe VVB (verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN1-VVG">
                  <desc>Probably NN1 (singular noun), but maybe VVG (-ing verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NN2-VVZ">
                  <desc>Probably NN2 (plural noun), but maybe VVZ (-s verb)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="NP0-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably NP0 (proper noun), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PNI-CRD">
                  <desc>Probably PNI (indefinite pronoun), but maybe CRD (number)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRP-AVP">
                  <desc>Probably PRP (preposition), but maybe AVP (adverb particle)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="PRP-CJS">
                  <desc>Probably PRP (preposition), but maybe CJS (subordinating conjunction)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVB-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably VVB (verb), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVD-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably VVD (verb past tense), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVD-VVN">
                  <desc>Probably VVD (verb past tense), but maybe VVN (verb past participle)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVG-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably VVG (-ing verb), but maybe AJ0 (adjective)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVG-NN1">
                  <desc>Probably VVG (-ing verb), but maybe NN1 (singular noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVN-AJ0">
                  <desc>Probably VVN (verb past participle), but maybe AJ0</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVN-VVD">
                  <desc>Probably VVN (verb past participle), but maybe VVD (verb past tense)</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="VVZ-NN2">
                  <desc>Probably VVZ (-s verb), but maybe NN2 (plural noun)</desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="xairaItem">
          <desc>provides data needed to define one part of a  xaira specification. </desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="ident">
              <desc>supplies a unique identifier.</desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="ns">
              <desc>supplies the namespace within which the identifier is to be
found. </desc>
            </attDef>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>indicates what is defined by this part of the specification.</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="element">
                  <desc> an element and its attributes.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="form">
                  <desc>a lexical form. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="addKey">
                  <desc>an additional key. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lemmaScheme">
                  <desc>a lemmatization scheme.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="region">
                  <desc>a region.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="textRef">
                  <desc>the reference used to identify
a document in the corpus.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="scopeRef">
                  <desc>the default scope for results
obtained from a corpus.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="unitRef">
                  <desc>the reference used to identify
some segmentation of a corpus document.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="indexPol">
                  <desc>the indexing policy for some
corpus component.</desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="defaultLang">
                  <desc>the default language for
a corpus. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="langRules">
                  <desc>any additional tokenization or
collation rules for some language used in a corpus. </desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="xairaList">
          <desc>contains a list of xaira parameters of a particular type</desc>
          <attList>
            <attDef ident="type">
              <desc>indicates the function of this part of the specification.</desc>
              <valList>
                <valItem ident="elementSpec">
                  <desc>lists and glosses the elements,
attributes, and codebooks used in a corpus </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="keySpec">
                  <desc>specifies how items are to be indexed. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="lemmaSpec">
                  <desc>specifies any lemmatization schemes
used. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="rangeSpec">
                  <desc>specifies any predefined ranges to be
made available to the client. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="refSpec">
                  <desc>specifies how items are to be referenced. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="indexSpec">
                  <desc>specifies any special indexing
policies. </desc>
                </valItem>
                <valItem ident="langSpec">
                  <desc>specifies any language-specific rules. </desc>
                </valItem>
              </valList>
            </attDef>
          </attList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="element" ident="xairaSpecification">
          <desc>specifies additional information needed by xaira. </desc>
        </xairaItem>
      </xairaList>
      <xairaList type="keySpec">
        <xairaItem type="form">
          <valSource type="element" ident="c"/>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="form">
          <valSource type="element" ident="w"/>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="addKey" ident="c5">
          <valSource type="attribute" ident="c5">
            <nameList>
              <gi>w</gi>
<!--              <gi>mw</gi>-->
              <gi>c</gi>
            </nameList>
            <defaultVal>XXX</defaultVal>
          </valSource>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="addKey" ident="Headword">
          <valSource type="attribute" ident="hw">
            <nameList>
              <gi>w</gi>
            </nameList>
          </valSource>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="addKey" ident="pos">
          <valSource type="attribute" ident="pos">
            <nameList>
              <gi>w</gi>
            </nameList>
            <defaultVal>XXX</defaultVal>
          </valSource>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem ident="region" type="addKey">
          <desc>defines the additional keys used to support filtering of text
from different regions of selected texts</desc>
          <valSource caseFold="false" ident="name()" type="pseudo">
            <nameList>
              <gi>stext</gi>
              <gi>teiHeader</gi>
              <gi>wtext</gi>
            </nameList>
            <defaultVal>nowhere</defaultVal>
          </valSource>
        </xairaItem>
      </xairaList>
      <xairaList type="lemmaSpec">
        <xairaItem type="lemmaScheme" ident="BNC">
          <nameList>
            <ident>Headword</ident>
            <ident>pos</ident>
          </nameList>
        </xairaItem>
      </xairaList>
      <xairaList type="regionSpec">
        <xairaItem type="region" ident="textOnly">
          <nameList>
            <ident>region</ident>
            <gi>stext</gi>
            <gi>wtext</gi>
          </nameList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="region" ident="speechOnly">
          <nameList>
            <ident>region</ident>
            <gi>stext</gi>
          </nameList>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="region" ident="headerOnly">
          <nameList>
            <ident>region</ident>
            <gi>teiHeader</gi>
          </nameList>
        </xairaItem>
      </xairaList>
      <xairaList type="refSpec">
        <xairaItem type="textRef">
          <valSource type="attribute" ident="id" ns="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace">
            <nameList>
              <gi>bncDoc</gi>
            </nameList>
          </valSource>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="scopeRef">
          <valSource type="attribute" ident="n">
            <nameList>
              <gi>s</gi>
            </nameList>
            <labelGen>%1.%2</labelGen>
          </valSource>
        </xairaItem>
      </xairaList>
      <xairaList type="indexSpec">
        <xairaItem type="indexPol">
          <attributePolicy ident="id" type="jointo" ns="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/namespace">
<!--            <nameList>
              <gi>bncDoc</gi>
              <gi>category</gi>
              <gi>person</gi>
              <gi>recording</gi>
              <gi>setting</gi>
              <gi>taxonomy</gi>
            </nameList>-->
          </attributePolicy>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="indexPol">
          <attributePolicy type="joinfrom" ident="who">
            <nameList>
              <gi>u</gi>
            </nameList>
            <joinTo>
              <gi>person</gi>
            </joinTo>
          </attributePolicy>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="indexPol">
          <elementPolicy type="none" ident="revisionDesc"/>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="indexPol">
          <elementPolicy type="markup" ident="bibliography" ns="http://xaira.org/ns/1.0/bibliography"/>
        </xairaItem>
        <xairaItem type="indexPol">
          <attributePolicy ident="targets" type="taxonomy">
            <nameList>
              <gi>catRef</gi>
            </nameList>
          </attributePolicy>
        </xairaItem>
<!--        <xairaItem type="indexPol">
          <attributePolicy ident="type" type="taxonomy">
            <nameList>
              <gi>wtext</gi>
              <gi>stext</gi>
            </nameList>
          </attributePolicy>
        </xairaItem>-->
      </xairaList>
      <xairaList type="langSpec">
        <xairaItem type="defaultLang" ident="en-GB"/>
      </xairaList>
    </xairaSpecification>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <creation date=""/>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="en-GB">The language of the British National Corpus is modern British English. Words,
fragments, and passages from many other languages, both ancient and modern, occur
within the corpus where these may be represented using a Latin alphabet. Long
passages in these languages, and material in other languages, are generally silently
deleted. </language>
    </langUsage>
    <particDesc>
      <person ageGroup="X" dialect="NONE" n="W0000" role="other" sex="u" soc="UU" xml:id="PS000">
        <persName>Unknown speaker</persName>
      </person>
      <person ageGroup="X" dialect="NONE" n="W000M" role="other" sex="u" soc="UU" xml:id="PS001">
        <persName>Group of unknown speakers</persName>
      </person>
    </particDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
    <change date="2007-01-23">introduce wtext</change>
    <change date="2006-11-07">finalize header generation script</change>
    <change date="2006-10-07">add taxonomy descs and tax indexpol</change>
    <change date="2006-10-01">autogenerated xairaspec from bncxmlodd</change>
    <change date="2006-08-09">handedits following newhrdgen.xsl</change>
    <change date="2004-06-12">Last Xaira index run</change>
    <change date="2003-08-12">Final manual check before delivery to OU; revised taxonomy definitions</change>
    <change date="2000-10-11">Final manual corrections for BNC-W</change>
    <change date="2000-10-18">Further manual corrections for BNC-W</change>
    <change date="2000-01-08">Manually changed catdescriptions etc. for BNC-W</change>
    <change date="1994-11-30">Corpus Revision</change>
  </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
